<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An argument, proving that a small number of regulated forces established during the pleasure of Parliament cannot damage our present happy establishment, and that it is highly necessary in our present circumstances to have the matter fully determined being considerations upon what has been objected against standing armies in general.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1698</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 56 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A25780</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3634</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R12991</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12934393</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12934393</idno>
            <idno type="VID">95732</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A25780)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 95732)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 730:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An argument, proving that a small number of regulated forces established during the pleasure of Parliament cannot damage our present happy establishment, and that it is highly necessary in our present circumstances to have the matter fully determined being considerations upon what has been objected against standing armies in general.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for A. Baldwin ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1698.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Army.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:95732:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:95732:1"/>
            <p>AN ARGUMENT, PROVING, <hi>That a ſmall Number of Regulated Forces Eſtabliſhed during the Pleaſure of Parliament, cannot damage our Preſent Happy Eſtabliſhment.</hi> AND THAT It is highly neceſſary in our preſent Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances to have the Matter fully determined. Being Conſiderations upon what has been ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected againſt <hi>Standing Armies</hi> in General.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Jupiter Omnipotens, precibus ſi flecteris ullis,</l>
               <l>Aſpice nos, hoc tantum: &amp; ſi pietate meremur,</l>
               <l>Da deinde Auxilium pater, aique hoec omnia firma.</l>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Vir. Aene. l. 11.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>A. Baldwin,</hi> near the <hi>Oxford Arms</hi> in <hi>Warwick-Lane,</hi> MDCXCVIII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:95732:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:95732:2"/>
            <head>The Introduction.</head>
            <p>HAving for a Year, or upwards, expected ſome Ingenious Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jector or other to have appeared in Publick, with Methods how to make the <hi>Militia</hi> uſeful; and nothing being as yet adjuſted to purpoſe concerning ſo grand an Affair, I thought I owed the Country of my Nativity ſo much Juſtice, as to ſet the preſent Matter of Debate in as fair a light as I am capable.</p>
            <p>In order therefore, to begin: I muſt aſſume upon me the liberty to ſay That it looks as if all the Deſign of this Grand Affair was only to put down the <hi>Army,</hi> and to let the <hi>Militia</hi> do as well as they can.</p>
            <p>That the <hi>Militia</hi> are not at this time in any meaſure uſeful, the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers themſelves will ſave me the trouble of proving. And ſince no Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod as yet is preſcribed to make them ſo, I hope the General Zeal of Mankind, for His preſent Majeſty's ſafety, will excuſe me; and let no Perſon think it improper to have th Matter more maturely conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered.</p>
            <p>That Circumſtances of Time are much altered, is not to be deny'd. The pretence of the <hi>Stuarts</hi> reaches not to the Point: They had none of them a Competitor for the Throne, or a Potent King to oppoſe their Titles: Whereas with us the Caſe is quite altered; there is living in the Southern Parts a <hi>Prince,</hi> who was actually in the <hi>Throne,</hi> and is ſtill bellowing out his thirſty Deſires to return again to his People. And leſt a pretence of Age ſhou'd ſtart up as an Objection to his En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours, he has ſo managed Affairs, that he proclaims to the World he has a Lawful Son. That, as ſuch, he is acknowledged in the Place where he reſides, is more apparent than his Tule; and his Picture is moſt artificially conveyed about this Kingdom, to form in ſome <hi>Bigots</hi> an Opinion that he will one day ſtrive for a greater Spot of Land than that which contain'd his Double-Clout.</p>
            <p>Are there then ſuch Things in the World? And are there ſuch Men as really give Ear to his Future Title to theſe Kingdoms? And can we be ſo ſupinely negligent, as not to act in ſome proportion to avoid ſuch an Impending Storm? And what way under Heaven is more likely to
<pb facs="tcp:95732:3"/>diſappoint this Intended Project, than to have the preſent Parliament agree on a ſmall Number of <hi>Regulated Forces,</hi> not ſo great as to be capable of putting us into Fear; but at the ſame time, enough to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port the now <hi>Regnant Prince,</hi> and juſtify the Act of Succeſſion? If this be not highly Reaſonable, I am ſorry it is my Opinion; I am ſure I have a true Idea of our Miſery, ſhou'd that Act be ſet aſide. And ſince there has lately appeared a Book in Print, Intituled, <hi>A ſhort Hiſtory of Standing Armies in England,</hi> as much approved of by ſome, as condemned by others; I have endeavoured in this following Diſcourſe, as near as I cou'd, to ſplit a Hair, and to appear with that Temper and Moderation, as neither Party may have any juſt oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to complain.</p>
            <p>Truly this late Author has appeared ſo hot and virulent againſt Kingſhip it ſelf, that, in my Opinion, he has injured the Cauſe: For, by the way, Reaſon ſpoke in Railing Language, diſappoints the Purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes for which it was intended.</p>
            <p>And becauſe Occaſion is taken in this Pamphlet to commend the laſt Years Author of <hi>an Argument againſt a Standing Army,</hi> I will ſo diſtinctly and methodically examine the ſamè, that if I can poſſible, I will engage him to publiſh ſome more of his Oratory to the World, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe what he has yet advanced will prove to be tarniſhed in the wearing. He writes, I confeſs, like a Gentleman of Stile and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter; his Propoſitions plauſible, and his Pretences ſeem fair and popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar; but his Plebeian Principles are too plain to be concealed. And therefore with him I begin.</p>
            <p>For this ſeems to me the faireſt way to ſet the matter in the trueſt light: For, as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſays, <hi>Iron ſharpens Iron, ſo does the Countenance of a Man his Friend.</hi> Diſputes ſtrike out the Truth; and ſince ſome buſy Heads wou'd not let the Matter ſleep, but revive the laſt Year's quarrel to prepoſſeſs the preſent Auguſt Aſſembly, who might perhaps have let it drop: I think alſo, that on the other hand there may be a pretence of Neceſſity; but leave the whyole Matter to their Conſideration.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:95732:3"/>
            <head>AN Argument, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>THE Title page is enough to ereate in ſome per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons a prejudice to the Matter herein to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated; but waving all diſadvantages ariſing on that account, I ſhall venture to purſue my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign. In which I ſhall obſerve the Decorum of Manners, as much as conſiſts with the Subject I handle, and the Provocations given, under the Notion of a Friend to <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in following my Diſcourſe, I ſhall lay down theſe Two Propoſitions.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Firſt, I will prove a Spirit of <hi>Jacobitiſm</hi> in the Method he has uſed.</item>
               <item>And ſecondly demonſtrate, That a ſmall Number of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulated Forces</hi> cannot damage our preſent Happy Conſtitution.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The Firſt Propoſition is ſo ſelf-evident, that it carries Demonſtration along with it; for proof of which, we need repair no further than to the Joy the <hi>Jacobites</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prEſt on the late Disbanding-Vote; and they were only ſorry to hear that Any part of the <hi>Army</hi> was to ſtand, ſo great a Regard was ſhown to ſo brave a <hi>Monarch</hi>'s ſafety. 'Tie true, the Opinion of many well-affected Perfons clos'd in to grace this Champion's Triumph; I call not their Judgments into queſtion; for any thing writ in a popular manner, and a flouriſhing Stile, goes down glibly, like
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:95732:4"/>gilded Pills made by a skilful Apothecary; but afterwards the bitter Taſt diſcovers the Frand.</p>
            <p>And juſt ſo it is with our unknown Author, he uſes Artificial Circumlocutions, that you may not diſcern <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi>'s Voice from <hi>Eſau</hi>'s Hands; for after he has admired the Happineſs of our Situation, and made us more for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midable than other Nations think us, (but takes no no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of our Retreats and Diſappointments:) he daſhes all the proſpect of our Giory in telling us a great Secret, (viz.) <hi>That the King muſt pay a debt to Nature.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There were but few, who in the midſt of Proſperity, under the benign Influence of Heaven, in the <hi>Reign</hi> of our late Famous <hi>Queen Elizabeth,</hi> tormented themſelves with what ſhou'd happen after her Death! No! They priz'd the Benefit of a juſt Adminiſtration at a greater rate, than to have ſuch melancholy Fancies ſeize upon them; and yet at the ſame time, more depended on a fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture <hi>Succeſſion</hi> than does at preſent. And he who is ſo vers'd in Books, muſt have met with <hi>Dolman</hi> in his Turn; who tells you that <hi>Spain,</hi> then in her Grandure, as well as other <hi>Monarchs,</hi> more potent than <hi>Scotland,</hi> put in for a Claim.</p>
            <p>Shou'd I here attempt to muſter up your Regiment of Fears, it wou'd be the moſt numerous of all the Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments already Disbanded, or to be Disbanded; but yet I will Curtail them as well as I can, becauſe ſome per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons aſſert there is weight in them; and I leave the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to Judge of the Matter of Fact.</p>
            <p>The firſt is the Fear you have that <hi>the King muſt pay a debt to Nature.</hi> Let any indifferent perſon conſtrue the ſenſe of theſe words as much in your Favour as poſſibly they can; and I think they can make no other Concluſion from them, but that you miſtruſt the next <hi>Succeſſor</hi>'s Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, or this Fear need not have been made the Collonel of your Regiment. To back this pretended Fear, a whole
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:95732:4"/>File of Example, foreign to the purpoſe, are brought in to ſhow you a Scholar, and nothing elſe.</p>
            <p>'Tis not proper in this place to ſhow your Miſtake in Hiſtory, where in <hi>p.</hi> 12. you enumerate Countries to be free that are not ſo, and others to be in <hi>abandoned Slavery</hi> that are <hi>free;</hi> for rather than you will loſe an Occaſion to adore a <hi>Common-wealth, Poland</hi> muſt come in for a <hi>free Country;</hi> and this can be for no other reaſon, but becauſe it is Elective; for if the Conſtitution muſt be <hi>Monarchy,</hi> a popular Election is moſt after your own heart. Sure, Sir, you never regarded the Inconvenience of multiplying Votes for Elections to <hi>Parliament;</hi> if you did, you might from thence compute how much more dangerous it is in a greater Community of People.</p>
            <p>Next you fall on the Prerogatives of the Crown, and therein give an unmerciſul Broadſide: You think it dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous to have the diſpoſal of <hi>Houſhold</hi> Officers, <hi>Revenue, State, Law, Religion,</hi> or <hi>Navy,</hi> to be in the <hi>King</hi>'s Gift: I am aſhamed to argue againſt the Unreaſonableneſs of this Propoſition. Had he power to ſeize on your Wife, and make you a Priſoner without a formal Proceſs, it would be much harder: But alas, he cannot by law ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point you a Steward to your Eſtate, or a Court-keeper on your Mannor; and would you chuſe your own Servants, and he want his? Away, away, with ſuch an <hi>Argument.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Your next Fear is as little to the purpoſe as any of the other; you ſay, That <hi>the King with</hi> 20000 <hi>Men-beforê<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand with us,</hi> or <hi>but half that number, the People cane make no Bfforts to defend their Liberties.</hi> I would not deſire to be ſo unfortunate as to ſee a Bad <hi>Prince</hi> on the <hi>Throue;</hi> yet if I ſhould ſuppoſe (what is not likely to come to paſs in my Life-time) that <hi>Arbitrary Power</hi> be intended, I am ſtill of opinion it will not be worth any one's time to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt it. Pray what got the late King by ſeizing of <hi>Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> impriſoning of <hi>Biſhops,</hi> proſtituting the <hi>Succeſſion,</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:95732:5"/>and ſuch like Noble Actions, but only to live to curſe his <hi>wretched Stateſmen</hi> that adviſed him, and to deplore his diſmal Misfortune; and the Reſult of evil Deſigns ended in a Revolt from <hi>Tyranny.</hi> Nor could the countenance of a powerful <hi>Prince</hi> ever reſtore him. No man does Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief, but with a proſpect of Succeſs; and to make 20000 <hi>men</hi> capable to conquer <hi>England,</hi> is a ReFlection on our <hi>Bravery</hi> and <hi>Courage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And beſides, to accompliſh it, theſe Three Things are abſolutely neceſſary.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The King muſt be of an <hi>Arbitrary Temper,</hi> and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pular in his <hi>Army.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. The <hi>Officers</hi> muſt be <hi>Paſſive,</hi> want <hi>Property,</hi> and have no regard to <hi>Honour.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. With theſe <hi>Qualifications</hi> they muſt win the <hi>Hearts</hi> of <hi>the Army</hi> to <hi>fight;</hi> or what the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Officers</hi> at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt is to no purpoſe; and this not being probable, it ought not in any wiſe to be propoſed.</item>
            </list>
            <p>When the late <hi>King</hi> drew up his <hi>Army</hi> at <hi>Salisbury,</hi> what confidence had the <hi>Officers</hi> in them? And what conFidence had the <hi>King</hi> in the <hi>Officers</hi> when many of them led the way to the Prince's Camp? Or what Faith cou'd the <hi>Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers</hi> have put in the <hi>common Soldiers,</hi> had one not intended to revolt as well as the other? And yet theſe very <hi>Officers</hi> are thought to be dangerous in the eyes of ſome <hi>Politicians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And there ariſes alſo from theſe words (<hi>If the King have</hi> 20000 <hi>men before-hand</hi>) another Remark, which is, It muſt be meant our <hi>preſent King,</hi> becauſe it is ſpoke in that Tenſe. 'Tis ſtrange that you who writ to be Popular, ſhould betray your fear of a <hi>Prince</hi> whom moſt of your Readers will admire: You had better have ſtuck to your miſtruſting his <hi>Succeſſors</hi> (as was hinted before) than to fix a Calumny where it will not abide: For what occaſion have people to make <hi>Efforts</hi> under a Juſt Adminiſtration?</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:95732:5"/>
            <p>But now inſtead of mending the matter, your <hi>Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condriac</hi> ſeizes you; and the <hi>Fit</hi> ſeems to have a ſpice of the <hi>Gout, Stone,</hi> and <hi>Gravel,</hi> mingled with it; for you cry out in your pain, Oh the <hi>wretched Stateſmen!</hi> they are in your <hi>way,</hi> or you want to be in their Place. Then in another Twitch you cry out, <hi>Arm againſt the Power of the Court.</hi> Perhaps you meant the Power of the Courtiers, or at leaſt good manners might have thought ſo, beeauſe the <hi>King</hi> dates his Proclamations from thence, and I am ſo modeſt as to think you did not mean to foment Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, and that the King was out of your head when you penn'd that Paragraph. The next is a ſort of a Lame <hi>Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer</hi> in your Regiment of Fears; he looks as rough-hewn as an <hi>Oliverian Collonel,</hi> and can never riſe higher than a Drummer, and that Poſt I aſſign him, becauſe he's a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect <hi>Almanzor</hi> at huſſing of <hi>Kings:</hi> He ſays, That if <hi>Charles the Firſt had had</hi> 5000 <hi>men before-hand with us, we had loſt our Liberties without ſtriking a ſtroke.</hi> 'Tis a home Charge, and let thoſe who ſerv'd that <hi>good</hi> but <hi>unfortunate</hi> King, take it as they pleaſe.</p>
            <p>Then, Oh the <hi>Army</hi> will <hi>inſluence Elections!</hi> Pray, Sir, what is it will pleaſe you? for you ſay the <hi>Militia is not uſeful,</hi> nor a <hi>Standing Army ſafe:</hi> Muſt we then truſt all to Providence, and fall in a Ditch, and cry, <hi>Lord help us,</hi> and make no Efforts to get out? 'Tis the likelieſt way I can tell to reſtore the <hi>late King James;</hi> for make us but ſo far Quakers, and the buſineſs is done. If the <hi>Arm of Fleſh</hi> is not to be uſed, prevail with our Enemies to be quiet. When <hi>Joſhua</hi> fought the Lord's Battels, he encamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and loſt men, though he won the Day. When <hi>Sampſon</hi>'s hands were bound, the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> ſoon came upon him, but when he broke his hold, they trembled; and unleſs you can give <hi>Mathematical Demonſtration</hi> that all Parties in the preſent <hi>Confederacy</hi> will keep up to the niceſt Puncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lio's, you will find a Regular Force to be abſolutely neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:95732:6"/>
            <p>But alas, you roar out ſtill in your pain! now <hi>they will encompaſs the Parliament Houſe.</hi> if the preſent <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> were to meet on <hi>Salisbury Plain,</hi> and none but Sutlers to oppoſe them, then the <hi>army</hi> in diſguiſe at <hi>Knightsbridge</hi> might fall upon them. But pray, Sir, let me know wherein wou'd be their Intereſt? for if the <hi>Parliament</hi> Eſtabliſh them, and provide Methods to pay them, whence can any danger proceed? But of this much more ſhall be ſaid when I Treat of the ſecond Point.</p>
            <p>Then the <hi>Exchequer-Officers</hi> and <hi>Annuity-People</hi> offend you; they rely on <hi>His Majeſty's Virtue,</hi> and not the <hi>Juſtice of the Exchequer-Officers.</hi> Well puſht, Sir; but what ſignifies <hi>Virtue,</hi> when it muſt not be <hi>led into Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</hi> becauſe as you obſerve in the whole courſe of your Life, <hi>Mankind is inclin'd to do as much miſchief as lies in their power.</hi> God have mercy <hi>Cynick!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Many more of your <hi>Fears</hi> remain untold. The <hi>Army</hi> will <hi>vote Parliaments factious and ſeditious Aſſemblies.</hi> Then the <hi>Exchequer will be ſhut up;</hi> which, as you ſay, <hi>is but diſobliging a few Tally-Jobbers,</hi> and <hi>Three Millions thereby ſav'd;</hi> and all this, you add, <hi>Tyrant Neceſſity</hi> compels. <hi>A Jacobite Miſtreſs, a Penſion,</hi> or ſuch like Trifles does the Heat.</p>
            <p>I have for brevities ſake only, drawn up the <hi>Right</hi> Wing of your Battalion of <hi>ſears;</hi> and the other is left, as a Perſon does ſometimes with a Text, till another occaſion.</p>
            <p>From hence I ſhould have proceeded to the ſecond Propoſition; but before I touch on it, I muſt crave leave to run your Book over again, to view the partiality of Opinion which ſhows it ſelf.</p>
            <p>To rout any pretence that can be offered for a Regulated Force, you poſitively aſſert, That we are <hi>Inſuperable at Sea;</hi> but pray, Sir, allow ſuch Perſons (as are from Tarpawlins riſen by <hi>Merit</hi> to be <hi>Officers</hi>) to be judges in
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:95732:6"/>this affair; they ſure can ken as far as you, and they will tell you, that a Wind may be in our teeth at the ſame time that it may afford an Enemy time to Land in our ſight, and they perhaps may eſcape before the Wind turns; but yet to ſerve your purpoſe a much as I can, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe your Argument is weak, I will admit that the Wind may veer about, and make us capable of engaging them; and will alſo be ſo fair as to allow you another Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal, <hi>viz. That we may beat them;</hi> but then if the Men they have landed increaſe by acceſſion of diſaffected Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, who will be ready to join them, How will our <hi>Militia,</hi> which you own is not yet uſeful, ever be able to oppoſe them? The <hi>Army</hi> you have voted down, and ſure you cannot expect thoſe Gentlemen to be ſo good-natur'd as to get into a Body on purpoſe to venture to be knock'd on the head, when they were turn'd off by a broad-ſide of your fears; I ſhould rather think that they have great Souls, and will covet Foreign Service, and ſeek by their Swords that glory abroad which was denied them here. War is now grown a Science, and <hi>Rewards</hi> affixt to <hi>Merit,</hi> and they will ſcorn to linger out a life of inglorious eaſe, who have heard peals of Cannon in an Enemies Country; nor can all the precaution imaginable hinder any Subject of <hi>England</hi> from entring into the Service of a Prince in League with us; and on a ſudden a miſtake in breach of Articles may be committed, and War follows. Then let us pray for the ſucceſs of our <hi>Fleet</hi> for fear the <hi>Militia</hi> is not in order.</p>
            <p>But how if our Prayers ſhould not ſucceed, ſince we are told from every Pulpit that we are ſinners! how if a croſs Wind ſhould diſappoint the <hi>Seamen</hi> of ſhewing their <hi>cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage?</hi> why then we muſt go to Loggerheads at home, and we ſhall ſoon have the ſatisfaction to ſee whether an <hi>Army</hi> or <hi>no Army</hi> is ſafeſt; but, alas! experience then will be bought at too dear a price; then, I doubt, your Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:95732:7"/>which you advanced, <hi>viz. That the only way to Reſtore King</hi> James <hi>is to have a Standing Army to keep him out,</hi> will prove you a falſe <hi>Prophet;</hi> but what ſatisfaction will that be to the publick when they groan under ſuch a misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune? for ſuch things have been in other Countries as well as our own, and according to your own rule, <hi>what happen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed yeſterday may again come to paſs,</hi> for the <hi>ſame cauſes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the ſame effects in all Ages.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor need you have told us that our <hi>Rights and Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leges are equal to the King's Prerogative,</hi> unleſs you had a ſuſpicion that they are like to be invaded; but 'tis popular to rub up Princes with ſuch <hi>Stories,</hi> and often promotes you to a place where you may talk. A crafty way of arguing, ſtill to render the Regnant <hi>Prince</hi> ſuſpicious to his people; for if the <hi>beſt</hi> are to be miſtruſted, the <hi>worſt</hi> cannot be tolerated. <hi>If vertue muſt not be led into temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation,</hi> becauſe as you ſay, <hi>mankind will do as much miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief as lies in their power,</hi> how can any Form of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſubſiſt? But you are for having the <hi>Army</hi> march off, and let the <hi>Militia</hi> take its fate. But who, Sir, wou'd be for Materials to form <hi>Tyranny,</hi> when you ſay, <hi>they muſt give place to more expert Architects to finiſh the Building?</hi> Faith, Sir, you are talking of a Structure, and I can ſee none of the foundation-work; I hope the Edifice is built on the ſandy foundation of your <hi>fears.</hi> Truly you are much wondred at for having ſo mean an opinion of your own Countrymen, as to think that 20000 <hi>Men</hi> are capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to enſlave us; 'tis ſuch a reflection on the preſent <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia,</hi> that I wonder they can forbear reproving you for it.</p>
            <p>But you <hi>fear</hi> that their Number will increaſe, and ſay, <hi>the Militia can never be made uſeful whilſt there is a Standing Army.</hi> But for your inſtance of the diſcouragement the <hi>Militia Officers met with in the late Reigns,</hi> is no argument to think it will be ſo ſtill, for both may be of moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent uſe, and prove a curb to each other; of which I ſhall Treat a while hence.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:95732:7"/>
            <p>'Tis confeſt that <hi>Armies</hi> have done harm, and <hi>Militia's</hi> have been dangerous, but yet both under good Diſcipline may do us Service. I remember in the hot times of <hi>Whig</hi> and <hi>Tory,</hi> a domineering Lord Mayor by his appointment kept <hi>Juſtice</hi> from entring <hi>Guild-Hall</hi> with ſome Files of Muſqueteers: And you inſtance in the <hi>Duke of Monmouth</hi>'s <hi>Rebellion,</hi> That the Biaſs of many lay the wrong way, but yet they prevented Deſerters going in to the Enemy. But now comes in the <hi>unhappy Old Man ſinking under the load of Age and Misfortunes.</hi> A much kinder Expreſſion than you could afford the Father, who was the beſt of the two; for <hi>he with</hi> 5000 <hi>men before-hand with us, would not have let us ſtruck a ſtroke for our Liberties,</hi> as you aſſert. But I ſuppoſe you are driving at the Terms of Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modation, ſhould the unhappy Old Man return.</p>
            <p>'Tis ſtrange you ſhould affirm, That <hi>continuing the Army will pleaſe the Conſpirators;</hi> alas, Sir, that muſt be a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake, becauſe they know their <hi>Courage</hi> and <hi>Loyalty</hi> too well.</p>
            <p>Then the <hi>Heroes</hi> of this Age are much beholden to you for telling them that <hi>they are of a courſe Allay, with too much Droſs in their compoſition:</hi> Which can be but Ill Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture at the beſt.</p>
            <p>Much more I could ſay againſt what you advance by the way of banter; but I will haſten to my Second Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, <hi>viz.</hi> to prove, That a Small Number of Regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated Forces cannot damage our happy Conſtitution.</p>
            <p>And this I ſhall begin with a Propoſition of your own, <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>what you have offered againſt Armies in general, is not to extend to our own, which was raiſed by Conſent.</hi> If then the preſent <hi>Parliament</hi> ſhall think ſit to eſtabliſh a ſmall Number, and ſee them duly paid, they will as cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly be in the Intereſt of the <hi>Government,</hi> as much as any Community of Perſons whatſoever; for the old <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Proverb is ready at hand, <hi>Always be rul'd by him who
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:95732:8"/>bears the Purſe.</hi> This is ſo plain, that the contrary cannot be atteſted without falſhood.</p>
            <p>Nor is it poſſible they can (as you fear) ever vote <hi>Parliaments factious and ſeditious Aſſemblies,</hi> ſince from them the Fountain-head of that Spring ariſes, which ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies the preſent Exigencies of the <hi>Crown.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to come more regularly to the matter in hand, let us examine what muſt go to the Compoſition of ſuch an <hi>Army</hi> as you make us believe you dread.</p>
            <p n="1">1. By Natural Inclination the Soldiery muſt thirſt after the Ruin of their own <hi>Country;</hi> in which you muſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premiſe their Relations and Friends; which is incongruous <hi>in ſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Next the <hi>Officers</hi> muſt back them in this laudable Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking; and to make them ſuch immoral men, you muſt ſuppoſe faſter than Mr. <hi>Bays</hi> does in the <hi>Rehearſal;</hi> for a <hi>Prince</hi> muſt encourage ſuch a ſort of glorious Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief that <hi>Catiline</hi> himſelf could never conſpire; for they muſt neither have <hi>Property</hi> nor <hi>Reaſon:</hi> A very hard Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and too much ſowreneſs of Ill Nature appears to have it ever thought probable.</p>
            <p>For ſhame, Sir, let me not be put to the trouble of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futing ſuch an Argument; for I am ſo charitable as to think an Idea of the late <hi>King James</hi>'s Return run in your head, and that you dreamt over-night of a <hi>Rehearſal Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volution,</hi> when you penn'd thoſe Paſſages of <hi>Fear.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For you dread <hi>their Number will increaſe.</hi> And who ſhall increaſe them? If the Parliament does, we ought in good manners to think them in the right, becauſe they are always preſumed to be a Body of Wiſe and Sagacious Perſons. You may be of that Number, and he who writes ſo well, muſt needs have the advantage of Elocution, which will be always capable to turn the Scale: But if you think the <hi>King</hi> will do it of his own head, and ſhake off <hi>Parliamentary Power,</hi> I deſire you to furniſh me with
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:95732:8"/>a reaſon why you think ſo, becauſe I am wholly deſtitute of one at preſent. To loſe the Guſto of a Good Reign, for fear a Bad <hi>Prince</hi> may hereafter ariſe, is the Hypocon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>driac with a vengeance; and contrary to the Sentiments of the Ingenious Mr. <hi>John Oldham</hi> (my particular Friend), who ſays to this purpoſe,</p>
            <q>
               <l>We have a good <hi>King,</hi> and he deſerves laughter,</l>
               <l>Who troubles himſelf with who ſhall come after.</l>
            </q>
            <p>By what has been ſaid, it appears that no Army will endeavour to aboliſh that Power which ſees them duly paid; ſo that your <hi>Freedom</hi> and <hi>Engliſh Conſtitution</hi> is ſafe; and no danger of having the <hi>Parliament ſurrounded,</hi> unleſs it be to protect them in their Freedom of Speech; for inſtance, have we not now better Judges than thoſe that were <hi>durante bene placito</hi> men.</p>
            <p>A Protecting <hi>Prince</hi> need not be debarr'd the <hi>Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives</hi> of the <hi>Crown,</hi> ſince the Purſe is the Right of the <hi>Commons,</hi> who are tenacious on occaſion. The Male-adminiſtration of the late <hi>Reign,</hi> made that Bigotted <hi>Prince</hi> not think it convenient to truſt them together, leſt they ſhould find fault: And therefore when he had finiſh'd his Bloody <hi>Weſtern</hi> Progreſs, he never employed them, for fear they ſhould make a Scrutiny into that affair by intrenching on Property: But where <hi>Merit</hi> guides the Helm, <hi>Liberty</hi> and <hi>Property</hi> go hand in hand with Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A King of England</hi> pretends not to <hi>Abimelech his Power.</hi> Your <hi>Wife</hi> is your <hi>Property</hi> as well as your <hi>Eſtate;</hi> and no <hi>Prince</hi> who endeavours to leſſen his Peoples <hi>Rights</hi> ever ſate ſafely on this <hi>Throne.</hi> His <hi>Prerogatives</hi> are as great as <hi>a good Prince</hi> can deſire, and ſuch an one will not do all ill thing upon <hi>Property,</hi> or <hi>engage us in unhappy quarrels among our ſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:95732:9"/>
            <p>You are right in your hint when you ſay, That <hi>the long and tedious War in which we have been engaged,</hi> is ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the <hi>Power of France,</hi> not to our want of <hi>Courage.</hi> You need not have preſcribed our <hi>Arming againſt the Court,</hi> for <hi>Parliaments</hi> are called to pray into ſuch affairs. But I find you have the old way of wounding <hi>Princes</hi> through the ſides of their <hi>Miniſters of State.</hi> Thus <hi>Laud</hi> and <hi>Strafford</hi> fell, and then the <hi>Oak</hi> loſt his Head.</p>
            <p>Beſides, Sir, the late Reigns are not an Inſtance for this, and if we ſearch into the unfortunate Downfalls of <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, Richard,</hi> and <hi>James</hi> the Second, who try'd too far, we ſhall find what they got by the Bargain. And when the <hi>firſt Charles</hi> was ſuſpected by his <hi>Parliament,</hi> he ever after it <hi>grew leſs</hi> in the Eſteem of his People.</p>
            <p>Which makes me think that if he <hi>had had</hi> 5000 <hi>Men be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hand,</hi> it had ſignified nothing at all. Nor wou'd the Heroick <hi>Army</hi> the <hi>late King</hi> had, ever have brought in <hi>Arbitrary Power,</hi> had not <hi>Popery been intended;</hi> the Magna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimous Conduct of ſuch as quitted honourable Poſts proves my Aſſertion; and therefore you might have ſpar'd your indecent expreſſions.</p>
            <p>And pray what kindneſs did <hi>Cromwel</hi>'s 17000 Men do to his Cauſe? they only ſerv'd to help the <hi>Martyr</hi>'s Son to the <hi>Throne.</hi> And therefore whilſt we are at unity among our ſelves we need dread nothing. And 'tis malicious in you to ſuppoſe the <hi>Parliament</hi> and <hi>Royal Authority</hi> two different Things.</p>
            <p>But now you come to ſettle matters aright when you tell us the <hi>Army is to be kept up but till</hi> Europe <hi>is in better Circumſtances,</hi> but you interlard this Sentence with a Fear it will prove otherwiſe; and inſtance in the Caſe of the <hi>Prince of Wales.</hi> Why, Sir, this is no Jeſting matter, Manhood may ſteal upon him, and he may cauſe miſchief tho' he can do but little good.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:95732:9"/>
            <p>Why ſhou'd not the <hi>Parliament</hi> be Judges of the Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber ſince their Eſtabliſhment is owing to them? ſhou'd they prove dangerous, as you ſuppoſe, 'tis but withdraw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Pay, and they muſt ſink of courſe. But tho' you can aſſord your Country-men never a good word, this I will ſay for them, <hi>Engliſh men have Engliſh Hearts, and Britiſh Honeſty;</hi> and unleſs you deny me that Point your <hi>fear</hi> may vaniſh.</p>
            <p>And beſides, Sir, 'tis unnatural to propoſe that 500 and odd Gentlemen choſen from all the parts of <hi>England</hi> can ever Conſpire to Ruin themſelves.</p>
            <p>But alas, you ſay, it was an Army which <hi>Charles 2d</hi> left his Succeſſor, made him capable <hi>to bluſter to his Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi> and pray what ſervice did they perform? 'Tis true, before his Intentions were laid open they took a Weſtern Expedition in his Favour. But when he fell a Suſpending and Impriſoning contrary to <hi>Law,</hi> he ſoon found that when he wanted their Aſſiſtance the ſecond time, that he was diſappointed; for they rid faſter to cloſe in with our Preſent <hi>Glorious Deliverer,</hi> than they did before to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs a <hi>Proteſtant Invader.</hi> And the Caſe requires no <hi>Oedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus</hi> to unfold the Riddle. No Conſtitution cares to anni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hilate it ſelf; and wiſe Perſons are of opinion that ſuch a <hi>Complication of Cauſes</hi> will always happen on the like oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion.</p>
            <p>So that on the whole it appears that a Regulated <hi>Army</hi> can never (as you ſuppoſe) <hi>cauſe a violation of our Laws,</hi> or be <hi>built on our Deſtruction,</hi> tho' you think it as certain as that there <hi>is a Kingdom in Heaven.</hi> I find no Kingdom on Earth will pleaſe you, no not <hi>Poland</hi> it ſelf, for your — <hi>Arma Teneti</hi> look to the Purſe Bearers, <hi>the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons in Parliament.</hi> An <hi>Honourable Army</hi> will never raiſe that by <hi>force,</hi> which a <hi>Parliament</hi> gives to their <hi>Merit.</hi> And a <hi>French Miſtreſs</hi> will be of no force till another <hi>Charles</hi> the Second ariſe, ſo that the <hi>Exchequer</hi> is ſafe.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:95732:10"/>
            <p>But pray Sir let me ask you one civil Queſtion: Can 20000 <hi>Men,</hi> or leſs, over-run <hi>England?</hi> and cannot 300000 put you in a Capacity to think of our own defence? Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs you can prevail to have all the Store-houſes in <hi>Europe</hi> ruin'd; to make our Swords plow the Ground; and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Death to uſe any ſort of Military Term, you anſwer not the Point. I will ſuppoſe the <hi>Princes</hi> now in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federacy will keep the League, and many years it may go forward; but there may ariſe a <hi>King</hi> hereafter (as there did of old in <hi>Egypt</hi>) who knows not <hi>Joſeph;</hi> and ſince ſuch things have been, according to your own Rule, <hi>they may again come to paſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What you quote of Mr. <hi>Johnſon,</hi> ſhows him an angry Man, (and he had Cauſe to be angry,) for there was a time I wou'd not have been in his Coat: He ſays there <hi>is no Epithet for Tyranny;</hi> but I had rather be under the Hatches of a <hi>Proteſtant Prince</hi> than a <hi>Popiſh one,</hi> ſince we have ſo lately ſeen the ſad Eſſects of the latter. 'Tis much you did not admire him for wiſhing all the <hi>Biſhops of England Inn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keepers,</hi> becauſe their Sufferings were left out in their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Addreſs.</p>
            <p>But to haſten: In the laſt Age we were Sovereigns of the <hi>Sea,</hi> without the pretence of a Rival; and if you think we are ſo now, you and I differ; and this is all owing to the <hi>curſed policy of the late Reigns:</hi> And then if we are not, ſurely a <hi>force</hi> in which we may conſide is very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient; make you the <hi>Militia</hi> ſo, and we are all friends. Aſpiring <hi>Spain</hi> confeſt we cou'd then give Laws to the Floating <hi>Element:</hi> but the day is paſt; and beſides, we want Union among our ſelves to make us Formidable.</p>
            <p>Nor is it enough to aſſert we may prevent all by Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence. Report may ſpread about a Deſign for <hi>Poland,</hi> or a <hi>Plantation;</hi> and a ſpeedy way for Tranſport-Ships is now found out. Beſides, <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> have Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies enough in their own Bowels, to prevent their doing
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:95732:10"/>us any ſervice. And moreover, <hi>Foreigners</hi> give this Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of <hi>Engliſhmen, That we are too credulous;</hi> and ſo a Cheat may paſs upon us.</p>
            <p>You ſay <hi>there has been a Miſapplication of our Naval Force,</hi> which you add, <hi>were not the Effects of Chance or Ignorance.</hi> Methinks now you prove the Neceſſity of ſome <hi>ſtanding Force</hi> to prevent <hi>Treachery.</hi> No Hare ever doubled in her Files ſo dextrouſly, which makes it ſuſpected that Men of different Kidneys clubb'd for your <hi>Pamphlet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have nothing to do with your hard words of <hi>Ragamuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fins</hi> and <hi>Henrooſt-Robbers,</hi> which you beſtow on our <hi>Army;</hi> but let <hi>Bilbo</hi> look to that, becauſe they were not called ſuch Names in <hi>Flanders.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I cannot conclude without minding one thing, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you have ſcarce ſpoke any thing elſe to the purpoſe. You ſay a <hi>well-train'd Militia may be made uſeful:</hi> No doubt but it may, and the Methods you have laid down are incomparable good. You propoſe, <hi>The Nobility, Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and Free-holders of England,</hi> to undertake that Affair. In anſwer to which, I will poſitively aſſert, That all I have converſed withal decline the Service: Nor does it touch their <hi>Loyalty;</hi> 'tis an habitude to <hi>Eaſe:</hi> They love their <hi>Country,</hi> but <hi>Education</hi> has in a great Meaſure taken them off from the Vanity of admiring <hi>wooden Legs</hi> and <hi>broken Pates.</hi> Such <hi>Theatrical</hi> Entertainments will paſ Muſter, where others are the <hi>Combatants.</hi> So that they will nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſeek to be <hi>Officers</hi> in a <hi>Regulated Militia,</hi> nor accept of the Poſt they care not for; and ſurely a Man of <hi>Property</hi> may do as he pleaſes.</p>
            <p>But you may Reply, there are enough that wil. Yet, by the way, your main Point is loſt, when you endeavour to make us believe, that all will aim at it. If any thing made them, it wou'd be that of having the <hi>Honour</hi> to ſee the <hi>King</hi> at the Head of them.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:95732:11"/>
            <p>The number of the <hi>Militia</hi> you ſix, and the <hi>Exerciſes</hi> you preſcribe them, with the time of being out upon Duty, looks too unreaſonable to require an Anſwer. I will only inſtance in a few particulars. You would have the ſame Man who is liſted at firſt, not to depart <hi>till he is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged by his Captain:</hi> and the Caſe of the <hi>Horſe</hi> is as hard as the <hi>Man.</hi> Then you propoſe, that if we will not go <hi>our ſelves,</hi> nor can find a <hi>Tenant,</hi> or <hi>Servant,</hi> a <hi>Soldier</hi> that has been in the <hi>Army</hi> ſhall ſupply the <hi>place.</hi> Pray, Sir, will his bearing my <hi>Arms</hi> make him <hi>Honeſter</hi> in the <hi>Militia</hi> than he was in a <hi>Standing Army?</hi> You Know he was then a <hi>Ragamuſſin,</hi> and can Disbanding make my <hi>Arms</hi> ſafer in. his <hi>Cuſtody?</hi> I ask this Queſtion, becauſe you propoſe the <hi>Officers</hi> in your new modelled <hi>Militia to be appointed by the King.</hi> I hope in ſuch a Caſe you will take care of their Pay, and make it in ſome proportion to ballance the Trouble.</p>
            <p>But at laſt you come to the directing Part, and before you have Modelled your <hi>Army of Militia</hi> to be worth a Man's going out of <hi>a Village</hi> or <hi>Country Town</hi> to ſee them <hi>exerciſe,</hi> you propoſe <hi>Rewards</hi> and <hi>Honours</hi> to <hi>the moſt deſerving;</hi> and perhaps that will be aſſign'd to him who has the Fineſt Cloaths; and tho you grudg <hi>the Charge of a neceſſary War,</hi> you are for a great deal of <hi>magnificence</hi> when you are in <hi>Peace;</hi> which looks like a kind of a whim.</p>
            <p>But does not ſuch a <hi>militia</hi> look like a <hi>Standing Army?</hi> for if the <hi>King</hi> appoints the <hi>Officers,</hi> and the <hi>common Soldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> are taken out of the <hi>Army,</hi> where is the difference? and if they are as <hi>dangerous,</hi> I am ſure they are more <hi>charge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able.</hi> And if in their <hi>ſplendid Equipage</hi> they are neceſſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to face the Enemy it will animate the <hi>Invaders Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage</hi> to have a proſpect of <hi>Gain.</hi> For <hi>History</hi> informs us that when <hi>Alexander</hi> went to ſubdue the <hi>Perſians,</hi> he took Advantage to tell his <hi>Soldiers</hi> that they fought for <hi>Silver
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:95732:11"/>Head-Pieces,</hi> which ſerv'd but to encourage the <hi>Enemy,</hi> ſo that your <hi>Fine Clothes</hi> are only ſit for a <hi>Theatre.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for your Project of having <hi>the Third Part of your Eſtate go to the Militia.</hi> I fancy you have but a very few on your ſide. I am not for the Charge of ſuch a <hi>Raree-Show,</hi> but I find every Man thinks himſelf <hi>Happy</hi> in what he likes <hi>Beſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To aſſert as you do, That (<hi>a ſmall Army can be of no uſe to us,</hi> as being <hi>too few to defend us againſt an Invaſion, and too many for the People to oppoſe,</hi>) looks like a Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, and a wire-drawing your <hi>Propoſition,</hi> becauſe it reflects on the <hi>Courage</hi> and <hi>Bravery</hi> of our <hi>Engliſh Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution</hi> to think that a ſmall Number can oppreſs them.</p>
            <p>'Tis endleſs to Anſwer all that you have cram'd in for <hi>Arguments</hi> ſake; your <hi>French Author</hi> and Mr. <hi>Harrington</hi>'s <hi>Oceana</hi> are Foreign to the Purpoſe; and when my <hi>Lord Bccon</hi> treats of a <hi>Standing Army,</hi> he means ſuch an one as will give <hi>Laws,</hi> and not receive them; for thoſe Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies had their Princes Pay, and not the Peoples.</p>
            <p>Beſides you own <hi>the Artillery of the World is much chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged ſince thoſe Men writ;</hi> and by that Rule Circumſtances may be chang'd too, for ſince <hi>War</hi> is a <hi>Myſtery,</hi> the <hi>Plow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> had better buſie his Head in conſulting of proper <hi>Grain</hi> for his Ground, and leave <hi>Military Affairs</hi> to wiſer Heads.</p>
            <p>But you now run up and down, and ſhuffle from Place to Place; you call it a <hi>Myſtery,</hi> and ſtraight tell us <hi>the Dull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Noddle can comprehend it in a few Weeks;</hi> 'tis allowed that the words of Command may be ſoon learned, yet <hi>action</hi> is a quite different thing. Tho you ſay <hi>it may be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired in the Cloſet as well as the Field.</hi> And add, <hi>that Actual Experience in War is not Eſſential to a Standing Army or Militia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet at laſt you do Juſtice, and acknowledg <hi>the preſent Army has been train'd up in a long War, and has gain'd great
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:95732:12"/>Knowledg,</hi> but yet they are an Army, and muſt down.</p>
            <p>I muſt tell you once more, Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s Caſe is not a Parallel, ſhe had no <hi>Competitor</hi> for her <hi>Throne,</hi> when ſhe truſted to her <hi>Citizens.</hi> For the Juſt Puniſhment of <hi>Mary</hi> of <hi>Scotland</hi> had Ruined the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Intereſt here; and Old <hi>Sixtus</hi> at <hi>Rome</hi> Bellowed out his <hi>Anathema</hi>'s in vain.</p>
            <p>But why ſhould you tell us the <hi>Jacobite Intereſt</hi> is low? 'tis more than they will own over a Bottle. I hope they may never prove as <hi>Wiſe</hi> as they are <hi>Hearty,</hi> becauſe I do not love <hi>miſchief.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But alas, you will ſay, a <hi>Prince</hi> ſo well belov'd, needs not fear an <hi>Invaſion.</hi> 'Tis not good to be too ſecure; the <hi>fool</hi> in the <hi>Parable</hi> teaches us that <hi>Leſſon,</hi> and you your ſelf ſay, That <hi>if</hi> France <hi>recovers Breath ſhe may be danger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,</hi> which turns the <hi>Argument</hi> againſt your ſelf.</p>
            <p>I muſt needs ſay you ſeem to ſmell rank of a <hi>Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth,</hi> when you tell us <hi>we have not virtue enough for a Commonwealth,</hi> and that <hi>Oliver's Army was compounded of men of virtue, ſobriety, and Publick ſpirit;</hi> and inſtance it as a Crime <hi>that our Army went over to the Prince of Orange.</hi> 'Tis what one may call Thruſting home, and no Man at Back-Gammon ever play'd with his Tables ſo open as the Blots which here you ſet; but I was not of that Number, and ſo am the leſs concerned.</p>
            <p>But at the word <hi>Army</hi> your Blood chills, and a Bead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roll of Crimes are fixt on that Conſtitution. A Man can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be <hi>Honeſt,</hi> and in an <hi>army</hi> he either <hi>commits Quarrels, Murders,</hi> or <hi>Robberies,</hi> or elſe <hi>they deſtroy the Game.</hi> Then <hi>they quarter in Publick houſes;</hi> and where pray muſt your <hi>Militia</hi> Quarter? Sometimes you ſay, <hi>they take up private ones.</hi> If ſo, it was under the <hi>Adminiſtration</hi> of the <hi>unhappy Old man,</hi> as you call him, <hi>p.</hi> 15.</p>
            <p>But, dear Sir, your <hi>melancholly</hi> encreaſes, or elſe why ſhou'd you propoſe that in a juſt <hi>Reign</hi> there <hi>ſhou'd be an artificial Diſtribution of Quarters,</hi> in order <hi>to awe Elections.</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:95732:12"/>'Tis a groſs Affront on the preſent Authority, and fit to be Reprimanded; it looks as if you thought we had chang'd for the worſe. And as for the <hi>Inſolence of Oſſicers</hi> of which you complain, it will be remedied by making the Number leſs, and continuing only thoſe that are <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil.</hi> So this way your Family may be ſafe from that <hi>Nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous train of miſchiefs</hi> which you dread.</p>
            <p>You ſay, <hi>You wou'd not have the Army ruined by that Peace which their Courage and Fidelity has procured for their Country.</hi> But you go no further then to a <hi>Donative,</hi> and when that is ſpent they may <hi>Dig</hi> if they pleaſe, unleſs they are not aſhamed <hi>to beg.</hi> Perhaps they wou'd have taken the <hi>Thanks of the Houſe</hi> as kindly, and then their <hi>Donative</hi> had been in Print.</p>
            <p>To conclude, You grudge the ſpending 40 <hi>Millions</hi> of Money, and their <hi>turning to graſs a mighty Monarch for breaking the Laws.</hi> You have no Regard to our preſent Circumſtances, which turn highly to our advantage. And if I live to be old, I ſhall pride my ſelf in telling a ſuccee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <hi>Poſterity,</hi> That the <hi>Heroick</hi> Arms of <hi>William the Third, my lawful King,</hi> did by the Aſſiſtance of his <hi>Commons in Parliament</hi> procure from <hi>France</hi> an <hi>Honourable Peace,</hi> even at a time when diſcontented people among us Laugh'd at the Propoſal.</p>
            <p>And now having done with this famous Argumentator, (who laſt year obtained what the Tyrant <hi>Caligula</hi> did but wiſh for, for he trod on the Necks of his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies;) I will be ſo juſt to you, Sir, as to let you take your turn. Nor ought I in reaſon to beg your pardon, becauſe your freedom with Kingſhip tolerates another to give you a caſt of their Office. But leſt your Cenſure of a Perſon unknown, ſhould preſently make you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude that I belong to the Court, or (what is equally the ſame that I was ſet at work by them; I will for once do a work of Supererogation, and inform you that I have
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:95732:13"/>never been there, nor have I any Emoluments from the Crown, nor can I by merit propoſe any.</p>
            <p>This Prejudice then being removed, we will proceed to make ſome Obſervations on your Pamphlet; but 'tis writ in ſuch an inveterate Stile, that I cannot tell where, or in what manner to proceed.</p>
            <p>But becauſe I want to have done, I will read on at a venture. You have already been told, that you are falſe in the Hiſtorical part, and ought to juſtify your ſelf as well as you can. You tell us of <hi>Richard the Second</hi> and his <hi>Archers;</hi> but what <hi>Prince</hi> being forewarned by the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern Example of the late <hi>King,</hi> will venture <hi>his</hi> or <hi>Richard</hi>'s Fate? By which 'tis plain that Tyranny repays the <hi>aggreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing King,</hi> and makes it not worth his pains: But really, Sir, it is not fair to make <hi>our preſent King</hi> an Object of our Fear, who came over hither on ſo Brave and Generous a Deſign, without the proſpect of gaining what was after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards conferr'd upon his Merit. He, nor no other Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon could divine the <hi>late King</hi> would act as he did in the laſt Scene of his Fate: But he verified an old Saying, <hi>Quem Jupiter vult perdere prius dimentat.</hi> I can eaſily excuſe him for all he did, or ever intended, for opening this Blot in his Tables. When he returned from <hi>Feverſham</hi> with the Huzza's of his People, he could obſerve thus much, as to ſay, <hi>Well, I ſee they love my Perſon, though they hate my Religion.</hi> But he (<hi>Good Man</hi>) ſoon forgot all; and with a certain King in the Scripture, <hi>put off his Robes, and delayed not, but made haſte to be gone.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to go on: As for your Inſtance of <hi>York</hi> and <hi>Lanca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> (which you borrow from the firſt Argumentator) you ſay, That <hi>as ſoon as they gain'd their Ends they diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banded their Forces:</hi> This Animadverſion may be properly made, That <hi>their careleſs Security gave occaſion to the Inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Prince to be troubleſome.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:95732:13"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Queen Elizabeth</hi>'s Succeſs, her Virtue, and Integrity, can never be ſullied; ſhe was the Honour of her <hi>Sex,</hi> and her <hi>Countrey,</hi> but met not with ſuch diſſiculties to humble <hi>France,</hi> as now there are. And though I cannot be of opinion with ſome of his Reſidents in <hi>Foreign Courts,</hi> who ſay, <hi>He gave Peace to Europe;</hi> yet ſince by <hi>Articles of Peace</hi> he is become our <hi>Ally,</hi> we will ſay nothing of the matter.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Four Stuarts</hi> are ſo unmercifully handled, that 'tis a ſhame to make uſe of your Quotations: I believe Mr. <hi>Collier</hi> (if he reads you) will think you as fulſome as the Plays he reproves.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hiſtorians</hi> who have writ of <hi>James the firſt,</hi> allow him to be <hi>a Religious Prince,</hi> and <hi>a Supporter of the Proteſtant Religion</hi> to the utmoſt of his power, though he could not retrieve the <hi>Palatinate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Charles the firſt</hi> deſerves not that hard uſage from our hands; and whilſt an <hi>Act of Parliament</hi> recognizes the Day of his <hi>Martyrdom,</hi> you might have been more civil.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Charles the Second</hi> was a Man of Pleaſure, but ſo much a Gentleman, that he never treated his Inferiors in ſo rude a manner.</p>
            <p>With <hi>the late King</hi> you may be as free as you pleaſe, for I am none of his champions: I will only ſay, That it is very mean to triumph over the Unfortunate.</p>
            <p>I have read of a certain General (who I think was a <hi>Roman</hi>), he gaining of the Day over his Adverſary, met with an opportunity to plunder his Tent, and ſome Papers in his Cabinet were found, which were probable of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence; but generouſly diſdaining to take ſo mean an Advantage, he committed them all to the ſlames, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Curioſity of knowing the Contents. You never certainly read the Story, or you did not approve the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject; elſe ſure to Departed Princes you would have been more kind.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:95732:14"/>
            <p>You next come to the buſineſs of our preſent Revoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and here your Satyr for want of Matter flags at the ſetting forth: But yet you will have a fling, to ſhow us, That though the Evil Spirit was diſpoſſeſs'd for a time, yet he roſe again on the Coaſt of <hi>Ireland;</hi> where you ſay, <hi>Chance or Inadvertency</hi> made things go on but oddly, <hi>till His Majeſty's great Genius overcame it.</hi> Perhaps the raſh Cenſure of you and ſome others, made the Gallant Duke <hi>Schomberg</hi> dye before his time. But you add, <hi>This gave them occaſion to raiſe more Forces, upon pretence of Invading France.</hi> And was it really but a Pretence? I am apt to believe they did not think ſo in <hi>France;</hi> for the Damage we did ſome Sea-port Towns, evidences this Aſſertion al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt to a demonſtration.</p>
            <p>But now you begin to fall out with the <hi>Fleet.</hi> If we loſt Advantages more than we gained, 'tis more than the <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobites</hi> will believe. And be you, Sir, as angry as you pleaſe, I really believe we had never met with ſuch Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Conditions of Peace, if our <hi>Army</hi> which acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſuch Reputation in <hi>Flanders,</hi> had not puſht it forward; and now thoſe who kept the War out of our own Bowels, are with you the Grievance of the Nation.</p>
            <p>The Authority which printed the Liſt of 18000 Men in <hi>King James</hi>'s Service was ſo authentick, that the Printer was never call'd to account for it, tho' the then <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> made a Scrutiny into ſuch Affairs, which amounts to a ſort of belief that it might be true.</p>
            <p>You next talk of a new <hi>Plot</hi> was then ſaid to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered; as if the Government made <hi>Plots</hi> for their own advantage; and then caſt a Joke on thoſe <hi>who ſearched for Conſpirators,</hi> ſaying, <hi>That they found plenty of Fornication, but no Traytors.</hi> 'Tis too jocoſe an expreſſion and ſeems to leſſen that abominable Sin. Many more things you cram in to ſwell your book and make the <hi>Government</hi> full of mean deſigns. 'Tis ill manners, and likewiſe much
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:95732:14"/>untruth to think in particular <hi>that the Iriſh were awed</hi> with the Menaces <hi>of loſing their woollen Manufacture if they did not comply in keeping up the Army.</hi> 'Tis a piece of Arrogance and Impudence, and requires a good aſſurance to confirm. I find you are of the Number of thoſe who take more care to <hi>disband</hi> than <hi>pay the Army,</hi> tho' the Vote run to <hi>Pay and Disband.</hi> You are not contented with the King's ſaying, that <hi>he wou'd comply with their Deſires as ſoon as conveniently he cou'd.</hi> You know, Sir, the Funds given fell ſhort in ſeveral Branches, which made the <hi>King</hi> not capable to pay them.</p>
            <p>Had I time, I cou'd inſtance my ſelf ſome Errors in the <hi>Hiſtories</hi> you quote of <hi>Alexander, Caeſar,</hi> and others; but that I ſuppoſe you deſign'd for a banter on the Credulous. As for your Apprehenſions of <hi>Slavery under this King,</hi> it ſeems to have drawn you out of the way; for you affirm that <hi>you will not truſt any Man living.</hi> I hope, Sir, you keep no Shop.</p>
            <p>Then you inſtance many <hi>Towns that are delivered up ſince the Peace;</hi> recollect your ſelves, and ſee if there are none behind.</p>
            <p>Now you come to borrow of the old Argumentator, and ſay, <hi>That the Militia cannot be made uſeful till the Army is disbanded;</hi> but lay down no Rules to make it ſo after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards. And beſides, you ſatisfy no body that we cannot be <hi>Invaded,</hi> when the <hi>Army is Disbanded;</hi> but indeed I ought not to ask for what cannot be performed. To have a Beggar ask Twenty pound, is what we cannot ſpare, no more than you can a Reaſon to this Queſtion.</p>
            <p>You tell us <hi>we have now a New Parliament, uncorrupted by the Intrigues of the Courtiers.</hi> Thoſe who were of the laſt, and are of his, are much beholden to you for this Character. You next ſeem to infer, That you think our Nation not as good Soldiers as the <hi>Dutch</hi> or the <hi>Germans,</hi> for you lay down a new Project to manage a War without our being
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:95732:15"/>concerned, if <hi>the King of Spain dies;</hi> or at leaſt thus much it will bear, that you care not if <hi>France</hi> carry the Day.</p>
            <p>As for your <hi>final</hi> Device, you know it is took for a Banter: Nor does your project of <hi>Cales</hi> or the <hi>Mediterra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nean</hi> ſerve much to the purpoſe; for you admit that <hi>it may be neceſſary to ſend Forces to Spain,</hi> but wou'd have them be <hi>raiſed when they are wanted;</hi> as if thoſe whom you now Disband, wou'd Liſt themſelves on purpoſe for the Honour of gaining <hi>broken Pates, and wooden Legs.</hi> I agree with you that the <hi>King of</hi> France <hi>has Disbanded many,</hi> yet his Numbers are ſtill formidable.</p>
            <p>And now, to crown the deſign of your Book, you ſeem to tell us <hi>what the People will not do,</hi> before you know what their <hi>Repreſentatives</hi> intend, on whom they devolved their Power. I ſhall conclude with you, That <hi>we have a wiſe and a virtuous Prince;</hi> and why ſhou'd not all this baniſh your Fears?</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>LET not the Author of the <hi>Militia Reform'd</hi> think from hence, that he is ſhot-free; for tho' he is not ſpoken of, there is a certain perſon well known to the Writer of this <hi>Tract,</hi> who has Compoſed a <hi>Dialogue</hi> betwixt <hi>Brutus</hi> and <hi>Caſſius</hi> by way of Anſwer; but waiting for his <hi>Hiſtory of Tyranny</hi> in <hi>Latin</hi> and <hi>Engliſh,</hi> with which he has promiſed to oblige the Publick, and it being not yet ſeen, the matter is for the preſent deferred.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
